Well, the title says it all, but it's
not what I'm necessarily saying. It's
what Dr. Lane Norton says in a recent
video on collagen for skin. It's
especially confusing when we also have
voices like Dr. Brad Stanfield saying
the opposite. Collagen still gets the
green light for him. Although, they're
talking about the same new analysis that
condemns collagen supplementation. So, I
have a lot of work ahead of me to clear
up some of the confusion. Let's listen
in on Dr. Norton's points and then I'd
like to go a layer deeper.
>> Collagen supplementation looks like it's
a scam.
>> If you're taking collagen that melts
your glass, I have to agree. Don't
consume that collagen. It is a scam. Ah,
the joys of AI image generation.
>> One thing I've been very consistent with
is I am very skeptical of collagen
supplementation for the following
reason. You trying to improve your
connective tissue or your collagen. If
you eat collagen, if you ingest a
supplement, that supplement gets broken
down during digestion to the
constitutive amino acids, it's not like
you take in collagen and it just goes
right into your connective tissue.
That's not how it works. It gets broken
down mostly into single amino acids.
>> Okay, let me stop there because this has
been debunked. In fact, even Dr. Norton
has pointed this out in research in past
videos. What happens is that collagen is
hydrayed and broken down into its
constitcutive amino acids because as
that collagen protein because it is a
protein and like any protein as it
enters the stomach you have high
concentrations of hydrochloric acid
which is going to cause that
three-dimensional structure of that
protein to begin to unfold. It's called
dennaturation. Then you have pepsin and
pepsinogen which are going to begin
chopping those polyeptide sequences up.
Then when it hits the daduminum of the
small intestine, you have proteasis like
trison, kimotrien that are going to come
in and chop it up into basically like
one, two and three amino acid sequences
that those are what gets absorbed into
circulation and that is what your cells
your periphery end up seeing. So he's
exactly right here. collagen gets broken
down into single amino acids but
critically also as die and tripeptides
like shown in this study where we see
the deptide proline and glycine in the
blood of humans. That's important
because the argument isn't that cells
that produce collagen are taking up the
building blocks of collagen like glycine
independently, proline independently and
so on but that these peptides the two
and three amino acids still bound
together are bioactive. That means that
the collagen peptides bind to receptors
on the cells or get taken up inside the
cells and change the cell signaling. Not
necessarily that they get used to form
collagen themselves, although that's
certainly another mechanism. In
mechanistic studies, when scientists
apply collagen peptides to skin cells,
they react by producing more of the
structural proteins. Now, these studies
aren't perfect, but they do speak to the
bioactive ability of collagen peptides,
and there are plenty of other studies
that indicate the same. So, the main
point here is that yes, collagen
peptides contain the molecules necessary
to produce mature collagen in the body,
but that's not the main reason it's
argued that we should consume them.
Rather, the collagen peptides themselves
that we do absorb are bioactive,
convincing the cells to produce more co
mature collagen. That was a lot. Let's
continue.
>> So, if it's not increasing connective
tissue synthesis rates, then how is this
improvement happening for people?
Because we do have human randomized
control trials demonstrating that
collagen supplementation can improve
pain recovery outcomes that it can
improve skin elasticity, skin hydration,
reduce the risk of wrinkles. Why is
there a divergence in this research
literature? Well, a new metaanalysis
just got published looking at the effect
of collagen supplementation on skin
elasticity, skin hydration, and
wrinkles. And the overall take-home from
this meta analysis was that collagen
supplementation improves skin
elasticity, skin hydration, and
decreases the incidence of wrinkles. So,
that means I'm wrong about collagen
supplementation, right? Hold up. Hey,
hey. So, this is the meat or if you want
the lentil of the topic. this new
analysis. It says collagen supplements
work at improving skin against his
argument, but Dr. Norton is about to
shut that down. Just reading from the
discussion of the paper. However, in the
sensitivity analysis, now a sensitivity
analysis is where they remove each
individual study one at a time and see
if they redo the meta analysis if the
results still hold. And it's meant to
protect against a single study having
too much influence on the overall meta
analysis. So again, I read in the
sensitivity analysis excluding outlier
studies showing an extreme beneficial
effect, collagen supplements showed no
significant improvement of wrinkles and
a decreased effect for skin hydration
and elasticity. So basically, if you
look through this meta analysis, there
was one study that showed like this huge
benefit. And when they took that out, it
either nullified the results or
drastically decreased them.
>> I won't explain that further. Dr. Norton
does a great job. However, I think that
it's important to look at that data.
This is skin elasticity and it provides
an excellent example of Dr. Norton's
point. In short, if the studies move to
the right of the vertical line there,
there's an improvement in skin
elasticity. Notice that one
Jazza Jaca study. Let's let's just
pronounce pretend like just insert that
I said that study name correctly. It's
way out there. They might have been
talking about skin cocaine, not
peptides, but regardless, it has
significant influence on the total
result, which is displayed in this
diamond down here. So the researchers do
to Lane's point a sensitivity analysis
and remove that study and clearly the
diamond moves closer to the line
indicating a reduced effect. I do have
to point out though that even when we
remove these outlier studies, there's
still an effect in two out of the three
skin measures. But Dr. Norton comes in
with an even better argument. In fact,
this next argument was so good, it made
me reconsider my stance on collagen. But
more importantly, they did what's called
a subgroup analysis where they add an
extra differentiator in the inclusion
criteria and they separate out these
different studies and look to see if the
results still hold. Their differentiator
was funding source. So they separated
out studies funded by companies that
sell collagen skin products versus
studies that were not funded by
companies that sell collagen skin
products. And what did they find? I read
direct from the paper. More importantly,
in the subgroup metaanalysis, my funding
source, studies that did not receive
funding from pharmaceutical companies
showed no significant effect of collagen
supplements for improving skin
hydration, elasticity, and wrinkles,
while those funded showed significant
improvements in all categories. Then
they did one more subgroup analysis.
They did it based on methological
quality. I will read again from the
conclusion. High quality studies
revealed no significant effect of
collagen supplements for improving skin
hydration, elasticity, and wrinkles.
While lowquality studies did show their
beneficial effects for improving skin
elasticity. I do say all the time, hey
guys, if your only criticism of study is
the funding source that says more about
your bias than the researchers, and I
stand by that if your only criticism is
of that, but those studies also in this
meta analysis were of lower methological
quality. Okay, the bottom line is that
the initial conclusion of the analysis
that collagen supplementation improves
the skin was completely driven by
studies that were funded by industry
studies like skin company funded
studies. I agree with Dr. Norton on a
few things here. One, I too do not throw
away studies merely because they're
funded by industry. However, when we do
have independent studies not funded by
industry and they show a different
result, I will side with those studies
over the industry studies. And as Lane
explained quite well, that's exactly
what happens here. When you group just
the non-industry funded studies
together, collagen supplementation
suddenly shows no effect. That's quite a
bombshell and it's a wonderful argument
backed by data. So, in this case, I
agree we should downgrade the industry
studies. So, it was at this point in the
video that I thought I should begin
prepping my video, saying that I've
changed my stance on collagen
supplements. But, of course, I had to
look at the analysis for myself. And
when I did, I laughed. Here's why. There
are seven studies that the researchers
identified as being not industry funded.
So, independent funding. So, I decided
to open up all these studies
individually. It didn't take long for me
to notice a striking trend. In fact, I
didn't even need to open the studies
because even the authors of the meta
analysis that we've been going over
describe it in their own analysis. But
for impact, let me put all seven
independent studies on the screen now.
And I'd like you to take a guess as to
how many of these studies found collagen
supplements did not improve skin. In
fact, I'm going to color them green if
they found an effect, which we'd expect
few to see an effect, if any. And I'll
color them red if they did not find an
effect. Okay, have your guess in mind on
the count of three. One, two, three.
That's right. You aren't
misunderstanding. Although you might be
a bit confused and if you're color
blind, then you're also annoyed. The
point here is that only one out of seven
of the independent studies showed no
effect. Said differently, six out of
seven of the studies found an effect of
collagen supplementation. How about that
for a bombshell? In fact, it's a similar
point brought up by Dr. Stanfield in his
video on the topic where he discusses
the highquality studies as opposed to
the independent studies that we just
went over. The meta analysis uses two
different common measures of study
quality. And there were nine studies in
total that got the highest marks for
both of those measures. And we just saw
that when the authors looked at just
those nine studies, they concluded that
there was no benefit overall from
collagen peptide supplements. So you
might expect that none or at most one or
two of those individual studies may have
found benefits. But here's the surprise.
So of those nine studies, only one found
no benefit. Another one found mixed
result, but the other seven all showed
positive impacts from collagen peptide
supplements on aspects of skin aging. So
the point being the vast majority of the
independent non-industryfunded studies
as defined by the analysis researchers
showed a benefit of collagen
supplementation. Now of course this
raises a defining question. What's with
the all collagen naysaying then? Why did
the researchers conclude that the
independent studies did not show an
effect of the collagen supplementation?
Well, there are multiple reasons
actually. I won't be able to go over all
of them in this video because I try to
keep these shorter considering the
amount of feedback I get to keep things
shorter and we both know that this video
is already going to be long and focused
on statistics. If you're interested in
more explanation of all the statistics
and how collagen works, check out my
research platform, the Physiotic
Insiders. It's the way that I get to
keep doing this kind of work for you.
It's also filled with benefits like
having weekly videos, articles, a
private podcast, live sessions with me
and the community and much more. If
you're looking for an extra layer and
more applicable information, you'll find
it all in there. The link to join is in
the description. Let's discuss a bit on
why though. There are multiple reasons,
but one is that when you start out with
23 studies at the beginning of the
analysis and then you start segmenting
them based on different subgroup
criteria, you reduce the number of
studies available to find an effect. In
this case, we divide the studies by
independence of funding and quality of
study design. Beyond that, not all the
studies looked at the three main skin
metrics, skin elasticity, hydration, and
wrinkling. So that further reduces the
number of studies. In some instances,
the analysis went from 24 studies down
to one, two, or three studies. Since the
amount of available data is constrained
by the criteria placed on it, the
confidence in the result weakens to such
a degree that statistically speaking,
the result is no effect, even if there
might be an effect. Beyond that, in the
highquality study subgroup analysis, the
researchers do identify an effect. And
guess what? Those sub analyses tend to
have more studies, i.e. more data
included in the neighborhood of like 11
or 12 studies which correlates with my
point. Like I said, there's more to say
like some errors that I caught in the
analysis, but I don't want to lose half
the audience. So, I'll leave the rest
for my extended edition if you're
interested. None of this changes the
overall point, which is this analysis is
not as foolproof as we thought. There's
still huge opportunity for collagen
supplements to work. However, I want to
address two more excellent critiques.
One of them has been brought up by Dr.
Norton before, and that is that there
are no collagen skin studies that
compare against protein. All the studies
comparing against a placebo. But if
people are trying to figure out if
there's a unique effect of collagen as
opposed to simply eating more protein or
eating more glycine, proline, etc., then
we need randomized control trials
comparing them. Unfortunately, we don't
have any. Dr. Stanfield brings up a
particular study that compared against
protein for skin healing from burns that
indicates benefit of collagen, but I
would like to see more evidence. So, I
agree with Dr. Norton that we need
better studies and we need studies
comparing against protein and proteins
rich in amino acids that make up
collagen. A second critique that I would
foresee coming is that even with a few
studies, we should be able to show
benefits. I think this critique can be a
good one assuming that we're expecting
collagen peptides to turn Alpuccino now
back into Alpuccino from Scarface. Okay,
maybe I maybe I should pick a different
movie. We'll go with The Godfather. You
can choose whichever one you want. I
don't think that most reasonable people
in the collagen space are saying that
collagen peptides are going to be
life-changing. I could be wrong, but
this isn't my stance at least. Collagen
peptides seem to help the skin and
reverse signs of aging, but they aren't
going to turn the back the clock 40
years or anything. So, in that context,
I would fully expect a need for more
quality data to detect small to moderate
effects. That's a speculation on my end,
though. In the end, what's the bottom
line here? Well, I agree with Dr. Norton
on certain aspects, the protein
comparison, for example. But I'm still
leaning, although not strongly, in favor
of collagen supplements being a benefit
for the old facials. I don't think that
once you look a layer deeper at this
analysis that you get a convincing
argument against collagen, but that
doesn't mean that we don't need better
research. If you're interested in a
deeper dive on collagen for the face or
for the joints, check them out right
here and here. And thanks for tuning in.
I'll catch you next time.